Guide to the Western Highway Historical Collection M0314
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Western Highway Historical Collection
1888-1960
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Western Highway Institute
M0314
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Photographs, dealer catalogs, and specification sheets concerning trucks, mostly from the 1920s and 30s.
Scope and Content
Collection of photographs, dealer catalogs, specification sheets and other material concerning trucks, buses, trailers, and other vehicles for transportation, commerce and construction. Includes the products of Autocar, Trailmobile, Fageol Motors, Kenworth, Mack Trucks/International Motor Company, Reliance Trailer and Truck, Hilo Transportation and Terminal, and White Motor Company.
The Western Highway Historical Collection was founded in 1960 with the cooperation of the Western Highway Institute, primarily to preserve the records and pictures of the early days of highway transportation west of the Rocky Mountains. Donors include Randolph Brandt, E.E. Brower, W.D. Patterson, Don Pennell of Peterbilt Motors, Sam A. Simpson, William Tice, and E. Guy Warren. Some published material was transferred to general stacks where it is accessible by catalog.
While the focus of the collection is on the vehicles themselves, also depicted in photographs are drivers, workers, and urban/industrial locales infrequently captured on camera. Additionally, researchers may encounter all manner of businesses and occupations, including bakeries, dairies, gas stations, lumbering, passenger buses, house movers, and municipal projects.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Automobiles -- History; Trucks; Trucking; Transportation -- Photographs; Autocar Company; Fageol Motors Company; Trailmobile Company; Kenworth Truck Company; Mack Trucks, inc.; Reliance Trailer and Truck Company, inc.; White Motor Company; Hilo Transportation and Terminal Company; Western Highway Institute
- Autocar
  - Autocar Messenger, 1926 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Bound issues of promotional magazine (1 volume).
  - Autocar Messenger, 1920-1925; Bound issues of promotional magazine (5 volumes). (Box 1)
  - Autocar photo albums, 1920s-30s (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Five sets of bound promotional photographs.
  - Autocar photo album of road construction projects in Sierra Nevada, 1920s-30s (Box 3)
    - Yosemite Valley, 30 photos
    - Mono Lake, 3 photos
    - Leevining Canyon, 2 photos
    - Valley Springs, 7 photos
    - Calaveras, 1 photos
    - Jackson, 3 photos
    - Colfax - Gold Run, 2 photos
    - truck driving, 4 photos
    - Mystic (Truckee River), 3 photos
    - Lake Tahoe, 5 photos
    - Bijou -Minden Road, 1 photos
    - Pleasant Valley (Relocation of Yosemite VAlley Railroad) and Exchequer Dam), 6 photos
    - Lodoga, 5 photos
    - Sacramento River Canyon, 3 photos
    - Lake Almanor Dam, 13 photos
    - next generation, 3 photos
    - miscellaneous - includes the Calaveras Big Tree grove, 12 photos
    - mounted separately, many dated, 1930-31.; 20 photos
  - Autocar Trucks (Box 5, Folder 1)
    1 flier (printed after 1950) for the 1898 Autocar; 3 printed advertisement bulletins; brief outline of the history of the company, 1951; bound catalog showing construction process, etc.
- Fageol Motors
  Fageol was based in Oakland, and most of the photos here are set on the West Coast, including California, Oregon & Washington, along with some from Australia (they had a branch there) and one from Japan.
  There are quite a few non-Fageol photos filed here as well, including some from New York.
  - misc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes images of a christenings, a trade show display, offices, showrooms, advertising, technical drawings, and commercial copy with cropping and highlighting.
  - casual driving, rural roads & snow (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - misc. - towing, horse trailer, ferry, fire trucks (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - buses & coaches (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - dump trucks, construction, roadworks, etc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes images from Los Angeles and the Pacific Northwest
  - flat bed trucks, cabs, hauling (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - food hauling - produce, livestock, dairy, ice, etc. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - freight, drayage, moving (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - gas trucks, gas stations (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes images from San Francisco, Los Angeles and the Pacific Northwest
  - logging, lumber (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Los Angeles, Southern California (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Los Angeles - buses & coaches (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Most are Los Angeles Motor Bus Company
  - San Francisco (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - San Francisco etc. - gift of Randolph Brandt (copy prints) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Oakland/East Bay (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - San Francisco Bay Area - construction, etc. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - San Francisco Bay Area - produce, foodstuffs, etc. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pacific Northwest (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pacific Northwest - buses & coaches (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Pacific Northwest - Consolidated Truck Lines/Freight Lines (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Southern Pacific Motor Transport Co. Safety Coaches (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - misc. small photos (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Costa Rica (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - billboards (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - photocopies in numbered order (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Hilo Transportation and Terminal Co., Ltd. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  5 photos of sugar hauling equipment in Hawaii. Gift of Hilo Transportation.
- Kenworth (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Kenworth Craftsman, June 1960. Vol 18 #3; 4 prints of Kenworth, gift of Edwin S. Acker; 1 print Kenworth, gift John C. Springer.
- Mack Trucks (International Motor Co.)
  - Mack Trucks (Box 5, Folder 3)
    1912 price list (with 13 pictures); 2 printed sheets (front and back) inc. 5 pictures.
  - Santa Cruz - Union Traction Co. (Mack) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Transferred from Hopkins Transportation Library at unknown date
- Reliance Trailer & Truck
  - San Francisco - Reliance Trailers dealer catalog (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - San Francisco - Reliance Trailer and Truck Co., Inc. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Gift of William Tice.
    - Del Monte Creamery truck & tailer, 1926
    - Early low-bed (2)
    - Solid tire low-bed trailer
    - Experimental dump truck, circa 1926
    - Riverdale creamery truck & trailer
    - Reliance side dump trailer, 1926
      (San Diego Street R.R. Co.)
    - Alaska- special construction trailer, circa 1922
    - Bottom dump trailer for Santa Clara Co road maintenance.
    - Pierce Arrow truck, Reliance trailer (Soledad to San Francisco over San Juan grade, 134 miles, 12-13 hours), 1921-22.
    - Reliance building at 16th St., San Francisco.
    - Lane air brakes, 1921.
    - Pierce Arrow truck, Reliance trailer, (Glass lined tanks for Naitonal Ice Cream)., 1922.
    - Bekins Van & Trailer, 1927.
    - Peterbilt truck, Reliance trailer with the largest load of Redwood logs recorded, Ft. Bragg., 1952.
    - Logging truck & trailer, 1922.
    - Pacific Body Works truck & trailer, 1924-26.
    - Hay truck, 1924.
    - Hay truck
    - Lumber truck
    - 3 miscellaneous
- Trailmobile (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Gift of Trailmobile, Includes 10 photos of Trailmobile trucks (the following subject matter is also included in the photos:) Cincinnati, Ohio, 1919 (2); fairs (1916); parade; San Antonio, Texas, 1918; Gas stations, 1939 (Associated Oil Co.)
- White Motor Co.
  - White Motor Co. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Gift of White Motor Co. 1921 White truck (photo); Ad showing White trucks doing rescue work during floods in Obio/Indiana, 1913; Pittsburgh flood in 1906, and other emergencies; Extract from the White Bulletin, 1906
  - White Motor Co. Growth of Motor Transportation talk by O.E. Dagner, May 8, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    5 pp typescript by O.E. Dagner (of White Motor Co.) for a presentation at a meeting of the Society of Automotive Engineers, accompanied by 26 photos and transparencies used in illustration.